Mss.B.L265
American Philosophical Society
L. L. (Lorenzo Lorraine) Langstroth papers, 1852-1895
Mss.B.L265
American Philosophical Society
1.0 ln. ft. ca. 300 items
Principally on bees and bee-keeping, especially correspondence and official documentation relating to Langstroth's efforts to win legal recognition of his invention of the movable-frame beehive. There are also fragments of an autobiography, newspaper clippings and pamphlets. Correspondents include editors of bee journals, and manufacturers and suppliers of materials for apiaries, as well as other apiarists. Some items of personal correspondence are also included in the collection.
Langstroth, L. L.(Lorenzo Lorraine),1810-1895.
Biographical/Historical note
Lorenzo Lorraine Langstroth (25 December 1810-6 October 1895) was a clergyman, teacher, and apiarist. He was born in Philadelphia, and graduated from Yale University in 1831. He was a Congregational pastor in Massachusetts, during which time he married Anne Tucker (1812-1873) and with whom he had three children. In 1848 he returned to Philadelphia to become the principal for a school for young women, when he also entered his avocation for bee-keeping.
In working with various kinds of bee hives, including a movable-frame hive that had been invented by Francis Huber in Switzerland, Langstroth was the first to formulate a different moveable-frame hive that better utilized the "bee space" partly by implementing a top-opening hive. (The "bee space" is a bee-sized gap left between the combs and the hive cover, large enough for bee movement but too small for the bees to create a new comb there.) With his new design, the cover board could be opened without unduly disturbing the bees. It also allowed the apiarist to remove individual combs and to easily examine the condition of the hive to implement corrective measures should they be needed. The construction further allowed for the removal of honey without disturbing the comb, which then allowed the bees re-use of the comb.
Working with cabinetmaker Henry Bourquin in Philadelphia, Langstroth created a complete hive with all-moveable frames, for which he receved a patent on 5 October 1852. Bourquin continued to manufacture these hives for a number of years, which Langstroth sold to other apiarists. However, the design was soon copied and entered even more widespread use, and for years Langstroth unsuccessfully sought to defend these infringements on his patent.
In 1858, Langstroth moved to a ten-acre homesite in Oxford, Ohio, where he took up bee-keeping full time. "Langstroth Cottage" is today a National Historic Landmark, a part of Miami University. Here with his son, James, he sold bees and apiary equipment.
Langstroth also was the author of several books on bee-keeping. During his career he kept in correspondence with numerous publishers of bee-keeping journals as well as other apiary suppliers.
L. L. Langstroth died while about to deliver a sermon in the Wayne Avenue Presbyterian Church, in Dayton, Ohio.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Anna L. Cowan, granddaughter of L. L. Langstroth, through Dr. Jacob Schramm. Accessioned May 1954.
Scope and Contents note
Among the correspondents this collection are represented:
H. Alley, publisher of "American Apiculturalist". Charles Dadant, of Chas. Dadant & Son, apiary suppliers. James Heddon, apiary supplier and publisher of "Bee-Keeper's Quarterly". John Hewitt, of John Hewitt & Co., an apiary supplier in Sheffield, England. Seth Hoagland, of S. Hoagland, apiary supplier. D. A. Jones, of D. A. Jones Ltd., apiary supplier in Ontario. Charles F. Muth, of Chas. F. Muth, apiary supplier and president of the Ohio State Bee-Keepers' Association. Thomas G. Newman, of Thos. G. Newman & Son, apiary suppliers and publisher of the "American Bee Journal". A. I. Root, of A. I. Root, apiary supplier and publisher of "Gleanings in Bee Culture". Samuel Wagner, publisher of the "American Bee Journal". George W. York, of George W. York & Co., apiary suppliers and publisher of the "American Bee Journal".
Separated Materials note
Accompanying this collection are a number of pamphlets, clippings, and a "Scrap Book" containing principally 19th century newspaper and magazine clippings about bee-keeping including items by and about L. L. Langstroth. While most if not all of the clippings to 1895 may have been collected by L. L. Langstroth himself, there is no record in this scrapbook to that effect. At least one 20th century clipping indicates that the scrapbook was added to. This collection is segregated into the APS's holdings of printed-materials, where individual items are separately cataloged. Each must be requested separately through the printed-materials catalog. To see the complete listing, search the printed materials catalog for Call no. 638.14 L26p).
Autobiographies.; Beekeepers.; Bees.; Clippings.
- Series I. Correspondence, 1854-1895
  Scope and Contents note
  See also OVERSIZE at end of finding aid.
  - Alley, H., 1892 June 24; 1.0 p.
  - Alley, H., 1892 August 1; 3.0 p.
  - Alley, H., 1892 August 4; 1.0 p.
  - Alley, H., [189-] August 1; 1.0 item
    Mailing envelope only. Annotations on envelope: "Alley--Aug 1--reply" and "About 'Punic' Bees".
  - Baldridge, M. M., 1863 November 2; 11.0 p.
    Includes 10 p. of copied "important documents" regarding the Otis affair. Copies of correspondence of Martin Metcalf with H. H. Manchester, and of Charles Alexander to Baldridge.
  - Baldridge, M. M., 1888 January 25; 4.0 p.
  - Baldridge, M. M., 1888 March 9; 2.0 p.
    "Confidential."
  - Baldridge, M. M., 1888 March 16
  - Baldridge, M. M. [to Cowan, A. L. (Mrs.)], 1894 February 6; 4.0 p.
  - Baldridge, M. M., 1895 August 1; 4.0 p.
  - Baldridge, M. M., 1895 October 3; 9.0 p.
  - Coffin, Charles P., 1889 August 15; 4.0 p.
  - Cook, A. J. [Langstroth to], 1892 July 30; 1.0 p.
  - Cook, A. J., 1895 August 22; 2.0 p.
  - Cowan, Anna L. [to Baldridge, M. M.], 1894 February 15; 2.0 p.
    "Copy of letter sent."
  - Cowan, Anna L. [to Charles Dadant & Son], 1887 July 23; 4.0 p.
    [Copy 1.] Annotation on envelope: "About Pub. Book".
  - Cowan, Anna L. [to Charles Dadant & Son], 1887 July 23; 3.0 p.
    [Copy 2, with postscript.] Annotation on letter (Cowan?): "Please preserve this letter, as we have kept an exact cpy ourselves. We do not wish to use it, legally, but simply keep it for our own satisfaction."
  - Cowan, H. C. [to Charles Dadant & Son], 1887 July 27; 4.0 p.
    Letter written and signed by A. L. Cowan; "Dictated by H. C. Cowan."
  - Cowan, Thomas William, 1892 July 12; 1.0 p.
  - Dadant, Charles, 1872 January
  - Dadant, Charles [to Cowan, A. L. (Mrs.)], 1887 July 18; 3.0 p.
  - [Dadant, Charles] [to "Mr. Cowan"?], 1887 August 1; 2.0 p.
    "Our reasons for mistrusting Lippincott."
  - Dadant, Charles [to Cowan, A. L. (Mrs.)], 1887 August 1; 4.0 p.
  - Dadant, Charles, 1887 September 30; 4.0 p.
  - Dadant, Charles [Langstroth to], 1887 October 5; 3.0 p.
    Letter written on verso of printed forms that acknowledge contributions and solicit additional funds toward construction of new building for the Young Men's Christian Association, Dayton, Ohio.
  - Dadant, Charles, 1887 October 24; 2.0 p.
    Annotation on envelope: "About an annutity from Dadant[']s".
  - Dadant, Charles, 1887 November 3; 2.0 p.
  - Dadant, Charles [Langstroth to], 1887 November 8; 1.0 p.
    "Extract of my letter to Dadant & Son"; re annuity.
  - Dadant, Charles, 1887 December 29, undated; 2.0 p.
    Letter is noted, "Copy". Verso is undated reply from Ch[arles]. D[adant] headed, "Confidential"; re editorial changes to book.
  - Dadant, Charles, 1888 January 27; 2.0 p.
  - Dadant, Charles, 1888 May 2; 2.0 p.
    Re: Heddon.
  - Dadant, Charles [Langstroth to], 1888 May 8; 2.0 p.
  - Dadant, Charles, 1891 March 28, undated; 2.0 p.
  - Dadant, Charles, 1892 April 18; 1.0 p.
  - Dadant, Charles, 1892 July 14; 1.0 p.
  - Dadant, Charles [Langstroth to], 1892 August 1
    Includes brief undated reply from "D&S" on recto.
  - Dadant, Charles, 1892 August 1; 2.0 p.
  - Dadant, Charles, 1895 August 8; 1.0 p.
  - Fisher, S. S., 1872 February 6; 5.0 p.
    Communicates to Langstroth a handwritten copy of "a communication to the Bee Journal": "Honor to whom honor is due", by Ch[arles]. Dadant, January 1872.
  - Gallup, E., [1893?] April 7; 4.0 p.
  - Grinnell, James S. [to Mrs. Langstroth], 1872 September 6; 4.0 p.
  - Heddon, James, 1888 May 7; 1.0 item
    Postcard.
  - Heddon, James, 1888 May 14; 1.0 item
  - Heddon, James, [1888?] May 21; 7.0 p.
  - Heddon, James [Langstroth to], 1892 May 26; 1.0 p.
    Letter marked, "Copy 3"; on verso, "Heddon--Copy".
  - Heddon, James, 1892 May 30; 4.0 p.
  - Heddon, James, [1885 May?]; 3.0 p.
    Three leaves; two headed "P.S.", one headed "P.S. 2", all with one envelope postmarked 1888 May 21.
  - Heddon, James, 1888 May-June, undated; 11.0 p.
    Several letters sent in one envelope (?), postmark 1888 June 30. Letters: 1888 May 28 (4 p.), 1888 June 4 (2 p.), 1888 June 7 (1 p.), 1888 June 30 (2 pp.), all on letterhead of "R. Heddon & Son's Real Estate Exchange". Also letter (fragment, last 2 p. only), date undetermined, on letterhead of "Office of James Hedden", apiary supply dealer.
  - Heddon, James, 1892 July 5; 5.0 p.
  - Heddon, James, 1892 August 4; 3.0 p.
  - Heddon, James, 1895 August 8; 5.0 p.
  - Heddon, James, undated; 3.0 leaves.
    Folder contains three sheets of blank "Short-hand Dictation" letterhead of James Heddon, apiarian supplies.
  - Hewitt, John, 1892 July 29; 1.0 item
    Postcard from dealer in Sheffield, England.
  - Hoagland, Seth, 1872 September 23; 2.0 p.
  - Hoagland, Seth, 1873 April 5; 2.0 p.
  - Jones, D. A., 1888 March 26; 4.0 p.
  - Kanden, C., 1864 February 10; 3.0 p.
    Letter in French to "Cher Monsieur"; addressed from France.
  - King, H. A. [American Bee Journal to], 1871 November 7; 3.0 p.
    Returns the enclosed manuscript (2 p.), titled, "Supplement to the Bee-Keepers' Journal. Important Testimony! The oath of August, Baron von Berlepsch".
  - Kleine, G. [to "Most honored Madam"], 1866 September 3; 1.0 p.
    "Translation from German by J. N. Langstroth". Addressed from Lüethorst [Germany].
  - Langstroth, A[nne]. T[ucker]. [L. L. Langstroth to], 1854 February 17; 7.0 p.
    Letter to "Mrs. A. T. Langstroth", Philadelphia, dated in New Orleans.
  - [Langstroth, L. L.] [to "My dear Madam"], undated; 1.0 p.
    Draft.
  - [Langstroth, L. L.] [to undetermined], undated; 4.0 p.
    Draft of letter. Written on three black sheets of printed tract; tract from George S. Wagner, Washington, D.C., "(Confidential.)", a prospectus for private sale of shares in "The American Bee Journal"; blind date printed on tract, "187_".
  - [Langstroth, L. L.] [to undetermined], undated; 1.0 p.
    Page 2 only.
  - Malin, W. G., 1864 September 24; 4.0 p.
    Letter apparently incomplete, 4 pages only.
  - Mann, A. M., 1871 March 27; 4.0 p.
    Addressed from London. "Private".
  - Munn, William Augustus [Langstroth to], 1863 October 8; 3.0 p.
    Certified Copy of Letter from L. L. Langstroth to Col. W. A. Munn"; certified by James Crawford, Justice of the Peace, Oxford Township, Butler Co., Ohio., for Col. W. A. Munn of London. Letter 1 p.
  - Munn, William Augustus, 1863 March 9; 2.0 p.
    Letter with illustration affixed.
  - Munn, William Augustus, 1863 November 9; 4.0 p.
    Letter folded and addressed, with postmarks. Letter has no salutation and begins in mid-sentence, indicating that a loose leaf is now absent.
  - [Multiple letters], 1895 August 6, undated
    Copies of letters from Langstroth; written on a single folded leaf:
    Baldridge, M. M. [Langstroth to] 1895 August 6
    Cowan, T. W. [Langstroth to] >1888; 1895
  - Muth, Charles F., 1885 November 20; 2.0 p.
  - Muth, Charles F., 1892 May 17; 1.0 p.
    Accompanied by tract: "Ohio State Bee-Keepers' Association. The Spring Management of Bees, The Marketing of Honey, etc. By Chas. F. Muth." (text of "President's Address"), 7 p.
  - Muth, Charles F., 1892 August 4; 2.0 p.
  - Muth, Charles F., 1892 August 11; 1.0 p.
  - Muth, Charles F., 1892 August 11; 1.0 item
    Postcard; follows up letter of same date.
  - Newman, Thomas G., 1888 February 13; 1888 March 10; 4.0 p.
    Two pieces of corrspondence, with extended comments on verso, by Langstroth, which could be drafts for correspondence or manuscript for comments to be published in a journal.
  - Newman, Thomas G., 1888 July 14; 1.0 p.
  - Newman, Thomas G., 1892 May 25; 2.0 p.
    Notation from Newman on verso: "I enclose Proofs".
  - Robinson, C. G. [Langstroth to], 1881 March 9; 2.0 p.
  - Root, A. I. [Langstroth to], 1872 January 4; 2.0 p.
    First two pages of letter only are present.
  - Root, A. I. [Langstroth to], 1888 May 24; 4.0 p.
    Edited draft.
  - Root, A. I. [Langstroth to], 1888 May 23; 4.0 p.
    Langstroth's text is complete, but torn second leaf shows that some additional text is now absent.
  - Root, A. I. [Langstroth to], 1888 May 28; 4.0 p.
    Headed, "Private and Confidential." Rubber stamp on first page: "Answered, May 29 1888 Flo. F."
  - Root, A. I., 1888 May 29; 2.0 p.
  - Root, A. I., 1888 July 10; 1.0 p.
  - Root, A. I. [Langstroth to], undated; 1.0 p.
  - Root, A. I. [Langstroth to], undated; 8.0 p.
  - Root, A. I. [firm], 1892 May 25; 3.0 p.
    "Dictated by J. T. Calvert." Includes invoice for 6 copies of "Old Unrevised Langstroth". Envelope includes notation about honey and butter purchase, and two quotations from Bible pertaining to honey and to butter.
  - Root, Ernest R., 1888 May 29, undated; 1.0 p.
  - Root, Ernest R. [Langstroth to], undated; 1.0 p.
    "Copy of letter of July 9th to Ernest Root." On verso of sheet is page 2 of another letter to an undetermined recipient; and either a postscript to this letter or the beginning of another letter dated 1888 July 9, recipient not indicated.
  - Root, Ernest R., 1892 August 1; 1.0 p.
  - Root, Ernest R., 1895 July 23; 1.0 p.
  - Root, Ernest R., undated; 2.0 p.
    Page 2 of Root letter only. Verso contains edited portion of a letter by Langstroth.
  - Smith, Addison M., 1871 March 16; 7.0 p.
  - U.S. Weather Bureau [Langstroth to], 1895 August 30; 1.0 p.
  - [Unsigned], 1871 December 21; 4.0 p.
  - Wagner, Samuel [Langstroth to], 1870 January 20; 3.0 p.
  - Wagner, Samuel [Langstroth to], 1871 February 13; 9.0 p.
  - Wagner, Samuel [Langstroth to], 1871 April 27; 5.0 p.
  - Wagner, Samuel [Langstroth to], 1871 June 16; 6.0 p.
  - Wagner, Samuel [to Fisher and Co.], 1871 October 10; 3.0 p.
  - Wagner, Samuel [Langstroth to], 1871 December 19; 4.0 p.
  - Whitney, E., 1871 March 22; 4.0 p.
    Annotation on last page: "Read this carefully--and return it when you next writ to us".
  - Whiting, Thomas, 1863 September 14; 4.0 p.
    Sender in Sheffield, Yorkshire.
  - Wiley, H. W., 1892 August 2; 1.0 p.
    "Copy of Wiley's letter to LLL". Variant 1.
  - Wiley, H. W., 1892 August 2; 1.0 p.
    "Copy of Wiley's letter to L.L.L." Variant 2.
  - Wiley, H. W. [Langstroth to], 1892 August 6; 2.0 p.
  - Wiley, H. W. [Langstroth to], 1892 August 22; 1.0 p.
  - [York, George W.], 1892 May; 2.0 items
    Unmarked galleys: (1) "Introductory Remarks.", signed, "George W. York & Co." (2) "Important Notice.", signed, "Thomas G. Newman." Regarding the sale of "The American Bee Journal" to George W. York and Co.
  - York, George W., 1892 June 15; 1.0 p.
  - York, George W., 1892 June 30; 1.0 p.
  - York, George W., 1892 July 27; 1.0 p.
  - York, George W., 1892 August 8; 1.0 p.
  - York, George W., 1892 September 21; 1.0 p.
  - York, George W., 1893 July 13; 1.0 p.
  - York, George W., 1893 September 5; 1.0 p.
  - York, George W., 1893 October 23; 2.0 p.
  - York, George W., 1894 March 24; 1.0 p.
  - York, George W., 1894 September 22; 1.0 p.
  - York, George W., 1895 January 9; 1.0 p.
  - York, George W., 1895 August 2; 2.0 p.
  - York, George W., 189-; 1.0 p.
- Series II. Legal Papers (excluding Court Documents), 1852-1888
  - Contract. Charles Dadant & C.P. Dadant with L.L. Langstroth, undated; 1.0 p.
    Regarding revision and enlargement of Langstroth's "A Practical Treatise on the Hive and Honey Bee".
  - Contract. L.L. Langstroth with Charles Dadant and C.P. Dadant, 1888 January 27; 2.0 p.
    Reassignment of copyright to Langstroth's "A Practical Treatise on the Hive and Honey-Bee".
  - Memorandum of Agreement. [and] Assignment. (O'Connor, Elizabeth), 1872 April 5, 1872 June 20; 4.0 p.
    Regarding reapportionment of share in O'Connor's patent on Improvements in Bee Hives.
  - Patent, 1852 October 5 [1860 July 18]; 18.0 leaves.
    True Copy of Patent issued to L. L. Langstroth, 5 October 1852, No. 9300, "Improvement in bee-hives". Copy, with Patent Office seal, dated 18 July 1860. Includes minor annotations, presumably as the result of legal investigations; this copy also has the notation, "Exhibit C." with a clerk's(?) signature. SEE ALSO OVERSIZE FILE FOR ACCOMPANYING DRAWING.
  - Patent. Caveat, 1868 March 28; 8.0 p.
    Transcription. "To the Commissioner of Patents &c Page 16 -- on the mode of constructing Bee Hives".
  - Patent Notice, undated; 28.0 p.
    Transcription of the text of Langstroth's patent for Improvement in Bee-Hives.
  - Power of Attorney. L.L. Langstroth to R. C. Otis, 1871; 2.0 p.
  - "To the Commissioner of Patents". Langstroth, Anne T., 1866 July 25; 10.0 p.
    On behalf of her husband, L. L. Langstroth, whose health "precludes the possibility of his making the necessary statement with regard to the pecuniary profit he has derived from the patent and the means he has used to publish his invention... ."
- Series III. Legal Papers. Court Documents and Papers, 1871-1873
  - Kidder v. Langstroth & Otis, no date; 4.0 p.
    U.S. Circuit Court, Eastern District of Wisconsin. Kimball P. Kidder v. Lorenzo L. Langstrtoh and Roswell C. Otis. Notice of Special Matter.
  - Otis v. Hamlin, 1871 February 11; 12.0 p.
    U.S. Circuit Court, Middle District of Tennessee. Roswell C. Otis v. J. B. Hamlin. Bill in Equity.
  - Otis v. King, 1871 February 8; 14.0 p.
    U.S. Circuit Court, Southern District of Ohio. Roswell C. Otis v. Homer A. King. Bill in Equity.
  - Otis v. King, 1871 May 13; 7.0 p.
    U.S. Circuit Court, Southern District of Ohio. The Answer of Homer A. King, Defendant, to the bill of complaint of Roswell C. Otis, Complainant.
  - Otis v. King, 1871 August 19; 2.0 p.
    U.S. Circuit Court, Southern District of Ohio. Roswell c. Otis v. Homer A. King. Notice of Examination.
  - Otis v. King, 1871 August 23; 13.0 p.
    U.S. Circuit Court, Southern District of Ohio. Roswell C. Otis v. Homer A. King. Testimony of Jacob Lowmaster, T. S. Walker, A. J. Flaherty, J. S. Zook, and John McBride.
  - Otis v. King, 1871 November 2; 3.0 p.
    U.S. Circuit Court, Southern District of Ohio. Roswell C. Otis v. Homer A. King. In Chancery. Stipulation as to Printed Matter.
  - Otis v. King, 1871 November 4; 2.0 p.
    U.S. Circuit Court, Southern District of Ohio. Roswell C. Otis v. Homer A. King. Notice of Examination.
  - Otis v. King, 1871 November 16; 2.0 p.
  - Otis v. King, 1872 January 24; 2.0 p.
    U.S. Circuit Court, Southern Ditrict of Ohio. Roswell C. Otis v. Homer A. King. Notice of Examination.
  - Otis v. King, 1872 February 21, 27; 4.0 p.
    L. L. Langstroth correspondence with solicitors Fisher & Fisher.
  - Otis v. King, 1872 February 24; 2.0 p.
  - Otis v. King, 1872 March 6; 16.0 p.
    U.S. Circuit Court, Southern District of Ohio. Roswell C. Otis v. Homer A. King. Second Amended Answer of Homer A. King, Defendant, to the Bill of Complaint of Roswell C. Otis, Complainant.
  - Otis v. King, 1872 March 29; 2.0 p.
    U.S. Circuit Court, Southern District of Ohio. Roswell C. Otis v. Homer A. King. [Notice of examination.]
  - Otis v. King, 1872 March 29; 2.0 p.
  - Otis v. King, 1782 March 29; 3.0 p.
    Correspondence, R. C. Otis to solicitors Fisher & Fisher.
  - Otis v. King, 1872 April 1; 2.0 p.
  - Otis v. King, 1872 April 11; 2.0 p.
    U.S. Circuit Court, Southern District of Ohio. Roswell C. Otis v. Homer A. King. "Agreed Amendment to 2[nd] Amended Ans[wer]."
  - Otis v. King, 1872 April 25; 2.0 p.
  - Otis v. King, 1872 April 26; 2.0 p.
  - Otis v. King, 1872 April 30; 2.0 p.
  - Otis v. King, 1872 May 4; 2.0 p.
  - Otis v. King, 1872 May 8; 2.0 p.
  - Otis v. King, 1872; 20.0 p.
    U.S. Circuit Court, Southern District of Ohio. Roswell C. Otis v. Homer A. King. Second amended answer of Homer A. King, defendant to the Bill of complaint of Roswell C. Otis complainant.
  - Otis v. King, 1872; 22.0 p.
    U.S. Circuit Court, Southern District of Ohio. Roswell C. Otis v. Homer A. King. The second amended answer of Homer A. King, defendant, to the bill of Complaint of Roswell C. Otis Complainant. Corrected Copy for Fisher & Fisher.
  - Otis v. King, undated; 8.0 p.
    Extract from the "Bienenzietung", no. 9 (May 1852), regarding communication of Berlepsch's sending to the editor "a sample of a hive invented by him". And commentary.
  - Otis v. King, undated; 4.0 p.
    Extract from "The Practical Bee Keeper" by John Milton,London, 1851, page 51.
- Series IV. Autobiographical Papers
  - "A Short Autobiography of Lorenzo Lorraine Langstroth", 1881 May; 6.0 p.
    Communicated to Charles Dadant. Incomplete.
  - Autobiographical notes, 1881 March, 1883 July 17; 12.0 p.
    Communicated to Charles Dadant. "I send you a breif [sic] sketch of my [sic] as requested by the President of the Central Bee-Keeper's Society of Italy."
  - Autobiographical notes, undated; 3.0 p.
    Fragmentary notes.
  - "Autobiography of an Old Preacher and Bee-keeper.", undated; 14.0 leaves.
    Typescript with holograph emendations.
  - "Personal Reminiscences of an Old Beekeeper", undated; 100.0 leaves.
    Autograph. 100 leaves, enumerated 1-102; leaves 40, 80 absent. Last leaf (p. 102) fragmentary. Leaves 1-7 (p. 1-7) have text on verso that seems to be a different draft, headed (partly damaged), "[Autob]iography of L. L. Langstroth[.] Personal Recollections of an old Clergyman and Bee-Keeper".
- Series V. Diaries
  - Apiary diary fragments, 1862 August, 1863 September; 4.0 p.
  - Personal diary fragments, undated; 20.0 p.
    Three fragmentary personal diaries; dated but not by year.
- Series VI. Manuscripts by L. L. Langstroth
  - "Comparison of Black and Italian Bees", undated; 3.0 p.
  - "Experiments in Wintering Bees", undated; 2.0 p.
  - "For the American Bee Journal", undated; 2.0 p.
    "... the importance of exercising greater care in admitting articles which deal in severe personalities."
  - Manuscript fragment 1, undated; 1.0 p.
  - Manuscript fragment 2, undated; 1.0 p.
    Regarding Langstroth's patent. Written on verso of tract, "To those desiring to visit the World's Fair" from McCormick Theological Seminary, Chicago.
  - Manuscript fragment 3, undated; 2.0 p.
    Regarding hives.
  - Manuscript fragment 4, undated; 4.0 p.
    Regarding Munn's hire.
  - Manuscript fragment 5, undated; 7.0 p.
    Two manuscripts, re Heddon patent. One paginated 2-7; the other only page 7.
  - "Pure Honey", 1872 August 22, undated; 11.0 p.
  - Verse, >1882 June; 2.0 p.
    (1) "Longings for Christ's presence in heaven." 1882 November 25. (2) Two untitled verses; religious content. Written on verso of "War Department Weather Map", "Precipitation Chart for June, 1882."
  - "Weather Forecasts and the Use of Magnetic Telegraph for predicting storms and saving lives and property, were probably first suggested by L. L. Langstroth", 1895 August 20; 5.0 p.
- Series VII. Extracts from Publications
  - "Homoeopathic Experience" by Dr. C. W. Wolf, Berlin, 1858. [in translation], undated; 8.0 p.
  - Undetermined source, undated; 2.0 p.
- Series VIII. Miscellaneous
  - "Bee Library of the late Rev. L. L. Langstroth.", >1885 October; 1.0 p.